In this demo, we'll be creating a program that utilizes arrays.
Once you're ready, fire it Visual Studio Code, and let's go.
Once Visual Studio Code loads, open up your demo directory.
We're on the Arrays demo, so click on Arrays, and then double click on Arrays.go.
For this demo, we'll be making a quick program that could be used by a clean service
to determine whether or not they've cleaned a specific room.
So what we'll need to do is create a room structure, we'll give each room a name, and whether
or not it's been cleaned.
The first thing I'll do, if we're functionality, is create a function that checks an array,
and determines which rooms are cleaned or not.
So this particular function will operate only on an array that's size 4.
We have a 4 here, so the array that we use has to have 4 elements, and it must be of type
room.
I'm then going to create a 4 loop, and my iterator variable is going to be i and set to 0,
and as long as it's less than our total number of rooms, then we will increase it by 1.
So the first thing I'll do in this loop is make a copy of the room, and most of the time
you'll want to do this, where you make a copy into a new variable, and this will help
once we get to this section on concurrency, because the i will change in one thread, but
not the other.
And so if you just make a copy, then you don't have to worry about any bugs popping
up.
We'll try to see if the room is cleaned.
So if cleaned is true, then we'll print out a message.
And otherwise, we'll print out a different message.
And that's all we'll do for that function, such as iterating through each room that we
have an array, and if it's cleaned, then we'll print out is cleaned, otherwise we'll
print out is dirty.
Next up, we need to make our array of rooms.
I'm going to use the ellipses that way.
We don't have to worry about how many are actually in here, and the compiler will figure
out for us.
So the first room will be in office, and then we'll have a warehouse, a reception, and
an ops section.
Ops can just be wherever they do their normal operations.
We'll then call the check cleanliness function with the rooms.
This function's going to go through each room, and it's going to print out whether or not
it's cleaned.
We didn't specify the cleaned variable here.
That means all of these are going to be false for that variable, because false is the default
value for Booleans.
We'll have a message indicating that some cleaning is being done, and we'll set a few
rooms to be cleaned.
So we'll set room 3 to be cleaned, and room 4 to be cleaned.
Remember that array started index 0.
So when we have rooms 2 here, that will be the reception.
So we have room 0, 1, 2, and then 3.
So we're going to have the reception and ops room be cleaned.
So when we run the program, it should indicate that those are cleaned on the terminal.
Last thing we'll do is just call this function again.
That way we can see if it's cleaned or not.
I'm going to hop into a terminal, and we'll run it.
We can run this demo with gorun.slashdemo/arrays.
And so we start out, everything is dirty because of default to false.
We perform some cleaning.
We then have the ops in warehouse are still dirty because they weren't cleaned, so that's
OK.
And then we have the reception clean and the ops being cleaned.
Real quick recap before we finish up, whenever you're working with the iterator variable
itself within a for loop, always make a copy.
So in this case, we're making a copy of rooms.
So we're using i here, so we need to make a copy of whatever we're using it with.
And if we don't do that, then you will for sure run into some bugs later.
So always make sure whenever you utilize the iterator variable within a loop, you're making
it in the context of a copy.
So we're copying room in this case.
And even if you just want the variable by itself without indexing an array, you still want
to make a copy of it.
So for example, you can just do something like this.
And now you can work with J from that point on instead of i.
This concludes the demo on arrays.
I'll see you in the next presentation.